<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version="2.0">
  <head>
    <title></title>
    <dateModified></dateModified>
    <ownerName></ownerName>
  </head>
  <body>
<outline text="Part I" _note="">
</outline>
<outline text="1: CHAOS">
  <outline text="&lt;strong&gt;Everything begins and ends in chaos.&lt;/strong&gt;">
  </outline>
  <outline text="&lt;strong&gt;Synopsis:&lt;/strong&gt; In the fundamental trinity of reality, that&#10;of chaos, energy, and order, chaos comes first. By definition, it exists&#10;before any &lt;em&gt;thing&lt;/em&gt; exists. It is the engine of creation and&#10;annihilation and the always-present foundation of all existence. Chaos&#10;exists across a spectrum that stretches between the 0 of nothingness and&#10;the ∞ of somethingness. This is the 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; duality of creation&#10;from which all that ever was, is, or will emerge." _note="In the fundamental triad of reality - chaos, energy, and order - chaos&#10;comes first. It exists by definition before any objects or things exist.&#10;Chaos is the driving force behind creation and destruction and is always&#10;present as the foundation of all existence. It exists along a spectrum&#10;that ranges from the 0 of nothingness to the infinity of somethingness.&#10;This is the first duality of creation from which everything that has&#10;ever existed, exists, or will exist emerges.&quot;">
  </outline>
  <outline text="&lt;strong&gt;Keywords:&lt;/strong&gt; chaos, randomness, pattern, duality,&#10;creation, zero, infinity" _note="The Oxford English Dictionary gives three definitions of the word&#10;*chaos*:&#10;&#10;-   The formless matter supposed to have existed before the creation of&#10;    the Universe.&#10;&#10;-   The formless and disordered state of matter before the creation of&#10;    the cosmos.&#10;&#10;-   A state of extreme confusion and disorder.&#10;&#10;I am not sure what the difference is between the first two definitions.&#10;Regardless, we’ll skip over the apparent contradiction of “formless&#10;matter” existing before creation… for now.&#10;&#10;Some colloquial, older definitions of chaos describe it as matter before&#10;there was any energy, but as we now know that matter itself is nothing&#10;but energy, that description no longer applies.&#10;&#10;There is also the Ancient Greek mythological definition of the word&#10;χάος, *Khaos*, referring to the void state preceding the creation of the&#10;Universe or cosmos and personified in the Greek creation myths as the&#10;god who was “*the first created being, from which came the primeval&#10;deities Gaia, Tartarus, Erebus, and Nyx.”*&#10;&#10;In physics, chaos is defined as “*The property of a complex system whose&#10;behavior is so unpredictable as to appear random, owing to great&#10;sensitivity to small changes in conditions*”, a. k. a. *The Butterfly&#10;Effect*, but as science writer James Gleick points out:[1]&#10;&#10;&gt; No one \[of the chaos scientists he interviewed\] could quite agree on&#10;&gt; \[a definition of\] the word itself, and so instead gives descriptions&#10;&gt; from a number of practitioners in the field. Those scientists that do&#10;&gt; have a definition are hardly in agreement, as Philip Holmes defined&#10;&gt; “chaotic” as “The complicated aperiodic attracting orbits of certain,&#10;&gt; usually low-dimensional dynamical systems.”&#10;&#10;… while Chinese theoretical physicist Bai-Lin Hao describes chaos as “a&#10;kind of order without periodicity”.&#10;&#10;Another term for *chaos* comes from cosmology, and that is the *primal&#10;void.*&#10;&#10;Modern cosmology’s Big Bang theory is quite compatible with this idea&#10;that before there was anything, there was nothing but a primal void, a&#10;term often used by cosmologists. The primal void is a descriptive&#10;synonym for at least one state of chaos.&#10;&#10;The primal void has also been called the *gap between heaven and Earth*,&#10;the *abyss*, *absolute-limitless nothing*, *ex nihilo*, *primordial&#10;waters*, and several other terms, all trying to convey the idea of an&#10;immeasurable nothingness, a concept that may well be impossible for the&#10;mind to grasp. This nothingness also includes (rather, excludes) the&#10;concept of time, as there can be no time in a void of nothingness, at&#10;least according to Stephen Hawking.[2]&#10;&#10;Everyone from scientists to mystics seems to agree on the rather obvious&#10;premise that before there was something, there was nothing, and then,&#10;presto, somethingness appeared in the nothingness. What that&#10;somethingness was is still unsettled. It could have been some form of&#10;singularity that may or may not have spontaneously appeared and expanded&#10;to create the Universe or some form of energy intense enough to warp&#10;space to the point where it became mass or even some type of&#10;multidimensional projection. In all these theories, and all beliefs and&#10;speculations, there is the understanding that before there was&#10;something, there was nothing.&#10;&#10;[1] Gleick, J. (1998). “**Making a New Science**”.&#10;&#10;[2] “**The Beginning of Time**.” Stephen Hawking,&#10;&lt;https://www.hawking.org.uk/the-beginning-of-time.html&gt;.">
  </outline>
  <outline text="Nothingness" _note="How “big” was this nothingness? Is there a limit to nothingness? If&#10;there is, how is that defined? If there is no limit, then is nothingness&#10;infinite? These may sound like silly questions, but they are actively&#10;being researched and debated in the worlds of science, philosophy, and&#10;mathematics[1].&#10;&#10;First, we must be clear about what we mean by *nothing* because&#10;conceptually, there are numerous types of nothingness (and many types of&#10;∞ as well, possibly infinite).&#10;&#10;According to various authorities, there are multiple levels of nothing,&#10;but a good overall understanding is provided by physicist *Sabine&#10;Hossenfelder*[2], who describes up to 9 levels of nothing. Below, we&#10;list these 9 levels, their 3 general categories, and the 2 basics&#10;concepts of relative and absolute nothingness that we will use in this&#10;book.&#10;&#10;What level would “I have nothing in my bank account” be categorized?&#10;Having a measurable balance of 0 puts your absolutely empty bank account&#10;in Level 6, and being a measure of the non-physical entity of credit&#10;puts it in level 7. Although being flat broke may feel like absolute&#10;nothingness, finances are a value that is derived from material things&#10;and is the transference of energy between things (people, businesses,&#10;etc.), and could even be considered a “field”, making your poverty a&#10;relative form of nothingness.&#10;&#10;*Relative nothingness* is contextual. *Absolute nothingness* has no&#10;context because nothing exists to give it context, so there is nothing&#10;that can be said about absolute nothingness. Even calling it *absolute&#10;nothingness* is limiting, as the concept of *absolute* implies “*to the&#10;largest degree possible*”, which implies size, measure, and time, none&#10;of which exist in *absolute nothingness*, and just adding words like&#10;*super-duper-ultra-unlimited* doesn’t fix this. Perhaps the only thing&#10;that can be said about true nothingness is that there is nothing we can&#10;say about it. In this way, primal, true, or absolute nothingness is&#10;synonymous with the *Tao* as described by Lao Tzu when he said:&#10;&#10;&gt; The Tao that can be described   &#10;&gt; is not the eternal Tao.&#10;&gt;&#10;&gt; The name that can be spoken is not the eternal Name.   &#10;&gt; The nameless is the boundary of Heaven and Earth.&#10;&gt;&#10;&gt; The named is the mother of creation.&#10;&#10;Which is to say:&#10;&#10;&gt; The nothingness that can be described   &#10;&gt; is not the eternal Nothingness.&#10;&gt;&#10;&gt; The nothing that can be spoken of is not the eternal Nothing.   &#10;&gt; The eternal Nothingness is the boundary of all that can ever be and&#10;&gt; all that is.&#10;&gt;&#10;&gt; Nothing is the mother of creation.&#10;&#10;If there are (at least) 2 kinds of nothingness, does that mean there are&#10;(at least) 2 kinds of dualities? Yes. Each of the 9 levels listed exists&#10;in some type of duality (except perhaps \#9) and has a duality of some&#10;sort, but with only 2 types of nothingness, we refer to only 2 types of&#10;duality; the *primal Duality*, which is the duality of the first *thing*&#10;that existed in the *primal nothingness*, and *relative duality*, which&#10;is every duality that exists because of, or within, the *Primal&#10;Duality*.&#10;&#10;We symbolize this primal duality as 1 and 0; from 1 and 0, all other&#10;numbers appear. It might seem more sensible that the primal duality&#10;would be that of ∞ and 0, which is also true, as ∞ is a concept&#10;representing the totality or unity of all numbers and is not a number&#10;itself, while the number 1 *does* represent unity, and is even defined&#10;as “unity”. In this case, which is limited to the context of *unity*,&#10;1=∞, or rather, the unity of 1 represents the unity of all, and the&#10;mapping the range of 0→1 to 0→∞ is common in mathematics and computer&#10;programming for exactly this reason.&#10;&#10;All the dualities that follow the primal duality exist in the realm of&#10;*relative nothingness*. We have names for these relative dualities, such&#10;as positive and negative, yin and yang, or any difference that separates&#10;*somethingness*. Measurement of any kind is a byproduct of relative&#10;nothingness. This *relative duality* is the duality of our reality, the&#10;mundane duality that allows *things* to exist, energy to move, and has&#10;states of balance and imbalance. In this context, balance refers to the&#10;balance *within* movement, and not the balance of stillness. Dancing,&#10;electricity, nature, the cosmos, these are all examples of balance&#10;within movement.&#10;&#10;Just as nothing must precede something, 0 precedes 1, so we can say that&#10;everything starts with 0. We will be using the concept of 0 and&#10;nothingness quite a bit, so let’s review this “simple” and common&#10;concept we use daily.&#10;&#10;[1] Sorensen, Roy. “**Nothingness.**” Stanford Encyclopedia of&#10;Philosophy. Stanford University, February 28, 2022.&#10;&lt;https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/nothingness/&gt;.&#10;&#10;[2] Hossenfelder, Sabine. “**What Is ‘Nothing’?**” Backreaction,&#10;September 24, 2022.&#10;&lt;https://backreaction.blogspot.com/2022/09/what-is-nothing.html&gt;.">
    <outline text="Zero" _note="The general concept of nothingness is represented by the number 0, but&#10;it was only recently in human history that we could even grasp the&#10;concept of nothingness, and even then, its adoption took thousands of&#10;years and was hotly debated. It is officially recognized that 0 was&#10;first recorded in Mesopotamia around 3 B.C.. Still, the ancient Indian&#10;*Bakshali manuscript* from 1500 B.C. appears to use the symbol of a dot&#10;(•) to represent 0. In either case, these were followed by 0’s&#10;appearance in Mayan Meso-America circa 4 A.D., again in Mayan&#10;Meso-America in the 5th century, Cambodia in the 7th century, and China&#10;and the Islamic countries in the 8th century. The concept of 0 didn’t&#10;reach Western Europe until the 12th century, and even then, it was not&#10;entirely accepted as a legitimate number concept for hundreds of years,&#10;which is a bit embarrassing considering that bees[1], monkeys&#10;[2],[3],[4], and crows[5] have no problem with the concept of 0.&#10;&#10;Similar to Dr. Elisabeth Kübler-Ross’ well-known 5 stages of grief;&#10;denial, anger, bargaining, depression, acceptance, the adoption of the&#10;number 0, according to animal physiologist Andreas Nieder, went through&#10;its own 4 stages[6], which seems appropriate as the concept of nothing,&#10;on an existential level, it not unlike death.&#10;&#10;-   **Stage 1:** Recognition of the absence of something.&#10;&#10;-   **Stage 2:** Recognition of nothing vs. something (5th c. BC,&#10;    Greece).&#10;&#10;-   **Stage 3:** Recognition of 0 preceding 1 (7th c. AD, India ).&#10;&#10;-   **Stage 4:** Ability to assign rules and properties to a symbolic&#10;    representations (13th c. AD, North Africa).&#10;&#10;*Note: these dates are best-guess estimates based on documented&#10;references.*&#10;&#10;Curiously, humans achieved such an advanced state of intelligence yet&#10;never developed the concept of 0. It’s almost as if humans were gifted&#10;the benefits of intelligence via genetic mutation, alien&#10;intervention[7], or psychoactive stimulation[8], thereby skipping a&#10;critical phase of the long, hard, slow work of evolution to get there.&#10;&#10;It is not a coincidence that the modern world and the concept of 0&#10;arrived simultaneously, as it was 0 that allowed for the creation of&#10;things like modern math and calculus. This ability of 0 began to eclipse&#10;the philosophical objections that you can’t get something from nothing,&#10;much to the chagrin of the Christian church, which was not very happy&#10;that this handy number was being introduced by the Muslims, not to&#10;mention that if something can come from nothing, what does that say&#10;about god? [9].&#10;&#10;[1] Howard, Scarlett R., Aurore Avarguès-Weber, Jair E. Garcia, Andrew&#10;D. Greentree, and Adrian G. Dyer. “**Numerical Ordering of Zero in Honey&#10;Bees.**” *Science* 360, no. 6393 (2018): 1124–26.&#10;&lt;https://doi.org/10.1126/science.aar4975&gt;.&#10;&#10;[2] Sulkowski, G. “**Can Rhesus Monkeys Spontaneously Subtract?**”&#10;Cognition 79, no. 3 (2001): 239–62.&#10;&lt;https://doi.org/10.1016/s0010-0277(00)00112-8&gt;.&#10;&#10;[3] Tsutsumi, Sayaka, Tomokazu Ushitani, and Kazuo Fujita.&#10;“**Arithmetic-like Reasoning in Wild Vervet Monkeys: A Demonstration of&#10;Cost-Benefit Calculation in Foraging.**” International Journal of&#10;Zoology 2011 (2011): 1–11. &lt;https://doi.org/10.1155/2011/806589&gt;.&#10;&#10;[4] Biro, Dora, and Tetsuro Matsuzawa. “**Use of Numerical Symbols by&#10;the Chimpanzee (Pan Troglodytes): Cardinals, Ordinals, and the&#10;Introduction of Zero.**” Animal Cognition 4, no. 3-4 (2001): 193–99.&#10;&lt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s100710100086&gt;.&#10;&#10;[5] Kirschhock, Maximilian E.; Ditz, Helen M.; Nieder, Andreas,&#10;“**Behavioral and Neuronal Representation of Numerosity Zero in the&#10;Crow**” Journal of Neuroscience 2 June 2021, 41 (22) 4889-4896; DOI:&#10;&lt;https://doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0090-21.2021&gt;,&#10;&lt;https://www.jneurosci.org/content/41/22/4889&gt;&#10;&#10;[6] Nieder, Andreas. “**Representing Something out of Nothing: The&#10;Dawning of Zero.**” Trends in Cognitive Sciences 20, no. 11 (2016):&#10;830–42. &lt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tics.2016.08.008&gt;,&#10;&lt;https://homepages.uni-tuebingen.de/andreas.nieder/Nieder%20(2016)%20TICS.pdf&gt;&#10;&#10;[7] As hypothesized by Dr. Immanuel Velikovsky, Erich von Däniken, and&#10;biblical scholar Zecharia Sitchin.&#10;&#10;[8] As hypothesized by entheogenist Terrence McKenna and&#10;ethnopharmacologist Dennis McKenna in their “Stoned Ape” theory of&#10;evolutionary leaps.&#10;&#10;[9] Seife, Charles. “**Zero: The Biography of a Dangerous Idea**”.&#10;London: Souvenir Press, 2019.">
    </outline>
    <outline text="The Complexity of Nothing" _note="0 is challenging enough without the added confusion that comes from the&#10;clearly ridiculous yet mathematically correct answer to 00=1 that many&#10;calculators provide (including Google’s calculator. The more realistic&#10;answer is *00=undefined*). However, X0 is always 0 as long as X!=0.&#10;Although this may look like math mumbo-jumbo, it’s pretty straight&#10;forward: X0=X1-1=$\frac{X^1}{X^1}$=$\frac{X}{X}$=1. In addition to 0&#10;representing nothing, this proof shows us how 0 also represents a state&#10;of nothing that *results from something*, as 1-1=0, or conceptually&#10;speaking, *something-something=nothing*. Hence, 0 is not only the “womb”&#10;from which all numbers emerge but also where numbers go when they&#10;disappear from context.&#10;&#10;I wonder if this is what Lao Tzu was also referring to in the *Tao Te&#10;Ching* when he said:&#10;&#10;&gt; Yet mystery and reality   &#10;&gt; emerge from the same source.   &#10;&gt; This source is called darkness.   &#10;&gt; Darkness born from darkness.   &#10;&gt; The beginning of all understanding.&#10;&#10;Which is to say (in this case):&#10;&#10;&gt; Yet the unknown and the known   &#10;&gt; emerge from the same source.   &#10;&gt; This source is called nothingness.   &#10;&gt; Somethingness born from nothingness.   &#10;&gt; The beginning of all understanding.&#10;&#10;This single number of 0 represents the antithesis of all other numbers,&#10;just as the idea that all that ever did, does, or will exist, does so&#10;because of the zen-like oxymoronic paradox of the “existence of&#10;nothingness”. Countless conjectures and proofs have been written on 0;&#10;that it is equal to 1, or to the sum of all numbers, or to ∞, or&#10;$\frac{1}{\infty}$ and many other, or even all, values. This is not&#10;hyperbole, as these concepts are hotly debated in mathematics and&#10;philosophy. On its surface, the statement 0=∞ looks like a senseless&#10;statement because 0 is a number but ∞ is a concept, so they can’t ever&#10;be equal. However, 0 is both a concept *and* a number, as it has a&#10;*quantitative* value of 0 and a *qualitative* value of *nothingness*.&#10;This is similar to how the number 1 has a *quantitative* value of 1 and&#10;a *qualitative* value of *unity*. Of course, all numbers are concepts,&#10;and most common numbers have well-known qualitative, but the first pair&#10;of *nothingness* and *unity* started it all. It’s worth noting that&#10;Parmenides, Leibniz, and other giants in the history of math equate&#10;*unity* with ∞ with the argument along the lines of all that *is*&#10;collectively defines the unity of existence; hence, the concept of 1=∞,&#10;which leads to concepts like $\frac{1}{\infty}$=1∴1-∞=0∴∞-1=0∴0+1=∞,&#10;etc., etc. While these concepts may not work so well quantitatively as&#10;when balancing your budget, they are fundamental qualitative concepts&#10;that have been examined by great minds, from Heraclitus to Hegel.&#10;&#10;The truth is, or rather *a* truth is, the numbers 0 and 1 are remarkably&#10;flexible as they are two concepts that encapsulate the idea of the&#10;nothing of nothingness and the totality of somethingness; the two poles&#10;that define the arena or spectrum wherein all things exist. What happens&#10;inside this arena? In a word: *order*. There is no order in the *nothing&#10;of nothingness* for there is nothing to order, and there is no order in&#10;the totality of somethingness as there is no form, structure, sequence,&#10;etc. If 0 is the mathematical concept of nothingness, then 1 is the&#10;ultimate mathematical black hole, and in that sense, 1 *does* represent&#10;∞. 0 and 1 (or 0 and ∞ if you prefer) are two states of chaos. Order&#10;only exists *between* these 2 states, and our understanding, discovery,&#10;and invention of order allow us to know this.">
      <outline text="&lt;strong&gt;Key 1:&lt;/strong&gt; chaos is a state lacking any order, time, or&#10;energy; total nothingness; 0.">
      </outline>
      <outline text="&lt;strong&gt;Key 2:&lt;/strong&gt; chaos is a state of total energy and matter;&#10;total somethingness; ∞">
      </outline>
    </outline>
  </outline>
  <outline text="Order and the chaos of 0 and ∞" _note="It was Newton’s contemplation of $\frac{0}{0}$ that led to his invention&#10;of calculus, and while we are taught that equations with 0 or ∞ are&#10;problematic and best to stay away from, calculus can prove that ∞∞, 1∞,&#10;00, $\frac{\infty}{\infty}$, 0×∞, ∞-∞ all equal $\frac{0}{0}$, and yet,&#10;even today, we are not sure what $\frac{0}{0}$ actually is. We can see&#10;evidence of this in current research, such as the research of the Chief&#10;Editor of the publication *Causation*, Ilija Barukčić, titled “*Zero&#10;Divided by Zero Equals One*”[1], which starts with:&#10;&#10;&gt; Objective: Accumulating evidence **indicates** that zero divided by&#10;&gt; zero equals 1&#10;&#10;And concludes with:&#10;&#10;&gt; Conclusion: The findings of this study **suggest** that zero divided&#10;&gt; by zero equals one.&#10;&#10;Or, in a paper co-authored by Ilija Barukčić that appeared in *Journal&#10;of Applied Mathematics and Physics* [2]:&#10;&#10;&gt; A solution of the philosophically, logically, mathematically and&#10;&gt; physically far reaching problem of the division of zero by zero (0/0)&#10;&gt; is still not in sight.&#10;&#10;In addition to this ambiguity, not only can 0 = ∞, it can equal any&#10;number. That is actually a true math statement (I didn’t just make it&#10;up). In math, when an answer can be many values, it is called an&#10;*indeterminate* answer, meaning an equation, like $\frac{0}{0}$, has no&#10;single or fixed value that can be determined (even though it looks likes&#10;the answer should be 1). The same can be said for&#10;$\frac{\infty}{\infty},\frac{\infty}{0}$ ,0×∞, 00, ∞0, 1∞, ∞=∞, as they&#10;are all *indeterminate*. Indeterminism is the equivalent of mathematical&#10;chaos, which supports our claim that 0 and ∞ are qualitative&#10;representations of chaos. They are also the only numbers that represent&#10;a concept that has no value; 0 being the explicit lack of any value, and&#10;∞ which is a concept that represents the opposite of 0 and yet can have&#10;many different forms. In general, and how it is used in this book, ∞ is&#10;meant as a frame for all positive numbers, as in *0 &amp;lt;&#10;positive\_numbers &amp;lt; ∞.*&#10;&#10;While the above is a mathematical argument for why 0 and ∞ represent&#10;states of chaos, we can also use the current definitions of chaos to&#10;make the same argument. While we can say that nothingness has no order&#10;or periodicity and is therefore chaotic, *chaos* also has another&#10;definition that means precisely the opposite, similar to the *∞=0*&#10;concept. Take, for example, the study of chaos in the origins of the&#10;Universe that was undertaken by Chicago’s Northwestern University&#10;physicist Adilson Motter, who concluded that 10-36 seconds after the Big&#10;Bang happened; there was a state of *total chaos*. Do you know what was&#10;happening at 10-36 seconds after the Big Bang? Everything, and in a&#10;temperature of over 1 trillion degrees. Motter concluded from his&#10;study:[3]&#10;&#10;&gt; “Now we establish once and for all that \[the universe\] is chaotic.”&#10;&#10;We are not claiming here that the Big Bang theory is correct, but we are&#10;asking the question; How can the concept of *chaos* describe the state&#10;of the void of total nothingness as well as the state of all matter and&#10;energy in the Universe, total somethingness?&#10;&#10;The definition of chaos that works for both is *“the degree that order&#10;is present in any state”*. Both extreme states of total nothingness and&#10;total somethingness have no order, pattern, or periodicity, which is&#10;quite compatible with another common definition of *chaos* as synonymous&#10;with *unpredictability*. A more flexible definition of *chaos* comes&#10;from the authors of “*Introduction to Complex Systems, Sustainability,&#10;and Innovations*”,[4], which simply states:&#10;&#10;&gt; chaos explores the transitions between order and disorder. An order&#10;&gt; arises from the ever growing disorder of the Universe - chaos and&#10;&gt; order together.&#10;&#10;But this is still too vague for our purposes because it is more&#10;reasonable to consider *chaos* as a spectrum from 0 to ∞. More&#10;correctly, the spectrum of *chaos* is the inverse of the spectrum of&#10;*order* (which is further defined later on), because just as there is no&#10;such *thing* as darkness, only a lack of the *thing* that is is light,&#10;chaos is the lack of order. For this reason, we initially define using a&#10;slightly inaccurate definition shown below. However, we will be refining&#10;this concept as we continue.&#10;&#10;[1] Barukčić, Ilija. “**Zero Divided by Zero Equals One.**” Journal of&#10;Applied Mathematics and Physics 06, no. 04 (2018): 836–53.&#10;&lt;https://doi.org/10.4236/jamp.2018.64072&gt;.&#10;&#10;[2] Barukčić, J. and Barukčić, I. (2016) “**Anti Aristotle—The Division&#10;of Zero by Zero**”. Journal of Applied Mathematics and Physics, 4,&#10;749-761. doi: 10.4236/jamp.2016.44085.&#10;&#10;[3] Northwestern University. “**Big bang was followed by chaos,&#10;mathematical analysis shows**”. ScienceDaily. ScienceDaily, 8 September&#10;2010.&#10;[www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2010/09/100907171642.htm](www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2010/09/100907171642.htm)&#10;&#10;[4] Thomas, Ciza, et al. “**Introduction to Complex Systems,&#10;Sustainability and Innovation.**” *Complex Systems, Sustainability and&#10;Innovation*, 2016, doi:10.5772/66453.">
    <outline text="&lt;strong&gt;Key 3:&lt;/strong&gt; chaos as a measure of pattern, order, and&#10;predictability." _note="Chaos is not the same as randomness. A random event is&#10;*non-deterministic*, meaning it can’t be determined when it will happen&#10;because it has no pattern, rule, or reason (that we can discover) and no&#10;known immediate cause. At least, that is how we define the word as it is&#10;used in this book. It may be the case that the concept of randomness&#10;simply exists to label unexplainable events that are actually chaotic in&#10;nature but far beyond our current abilities to understand, like a&#10;super-chaotic event. An example of this is from the website RANDOM.ORG,&#10;which generates random numbers. In order to make them more truly random,&#10;they use atmospheric noise as an input. That ambient noise is not random&#10;but is chaotic. Another example is how computer random number generators&#10;use electrical noise and heat as inputs to their number generator.&#10;Again, these are chaotic inputs.&#10;&#10;Another way to understand the difference between randomness and chaos is&#10;in the value of π (pi). The value of π is infinite in numbers and the&#10;sequence of those numbers is quite predictable using simple math, which&#10;is how we can calculate the value of π, but there is no pattern to the&#10;numbers, so there is no way to determine the following number based on&#10;the previous numbers. This is similar to how prime numbers can only be&#10;calculated as they have no pattern. This makes the value of π chaotic&#10;because the value is deterministic yet produces a series of numbers that&#10;appear random and uniformly distributed (a.k.a. *normal* distribution).&#10;We say “appear” because there is no way to prove that π is random or&#10;*normal*, just as there is no way to prove that the infinite numerical&#10;sequence contains every possible combination of numbers that can ever&#10;exist, but evidence suggests that’s *probably* the case[1]. So, chaos&#10;has a pattern, but it is unpredictable, and **randomness has no pattern&#10;and therefore contains *every* pattern**. Here we see an instance of the&#10;concept of not only 0=∞, but that ∞ exist *within* 0.&#10;&#10;&gt; There’s a beauty to Pi that keeps us looking at it... the digits of Pi&#10;&gt; are extremely random. They have no pattern, and in mathematics that’s&#10;&gt; really the same as saying they have every pattern.” **~Jonathan&#10;&gt; Borwein, mathematician**&#10;&#10;Depending on who you ask, you can get a number of different definitions&#10;of “random”, but the definition we will be referring to is:&#10;&#10;[1] Bailey, David H., Jonathan M. Borwein, Cristian S. Calude, Michael&#10;J. Dinneen, Monica Dumitrescu, and Alex Yee. “**An Empirical Approach to&#10;the Normality of π.**” Experimental Mathematics 21, no. 4 (2012):&#10;375–84. &lt;https://doi.org/10.1080/10586458.2012.665333&gt;,&#10;&lt;https://carmamaths.org/resources/jon/normality.pdf&gt;">
    </outline>
    <outline text="&lt;strong&gt;Key 4:&lt;/strong&gt; A random event is a spontaneous event with no&#10;apparent cause." _note="Of course, this leaves a lot of room for speculation as to the&#10;randomness of an event, as there are undoubtedly many cases where we&#10;just can’t see the cause. What appears as random could easily be related&#10;to the *butterfly effect*, which states that small changes can have a&#10;growing and cascading effect. This idea is often exemplified in the&#10;question, “*Does the flap of a butterfly’s wings in Brazil set off a&#10;tornado in Texas?*” which was also the title of a 1972 talk[1] given by&#10;Edward Norton Lorenz, a mathematician, meteorologist, and founder of&#10;chaos theory.&#10;&#10;While this is a bit of an aside, it is a fascinating piece of history&#10;and an excellent example of the *butterfly effect* in so far as how it&#10;can affect society and how a candid meeting of two strangers in a ball&#10;in Prague in 1896 would be responsible for World War I and World War II.&#10;&#10;![](/home/jw/books/tholonia/chapters/Images/sophie.png &quot;fig:&quot;)The two&#10;strangers were Arch Duke Franz Ferdinand and Sophie Chotek, a duchess&#10;and the daughter of a Bohemian Count, who met, fell in love, and got&#10;married. The problem was Sophia, being a mere duchess was not royalty,&#10;and given royalty’s strict adherence to their self-aggrandizing customs,&#10;it was forbidden that she appear next to the Archbishop in any official&#10;royal ceremonies. The Arch Duke may have loved Sophie, but he was still&#10;an obedient autocrat, and so he followed the rules. However, this meant&#10;he *was* allowed to have her by his side during non-royal ceremonies,&#10;such as when he was acting as the Inspector-General of the&#10;Austria-Hungarian Army. Taking advantage of this loophole, he decided to&#10;show off his wife to the world by taking a public trip to inspect the&#10;Bosnian army with his wife by his side. To ensure everyone saw them&#10;together, they traveled in an open car for all to see. It was during&#10;this public demonstration of his undying love that the Serbian&#10;nationalist, Gavrilo Princip, ran up to the car and shot both of them at&#10;point-blank range, killing them instantly.&#10;&#10;Austria was outraged, demanding an apology from Serbia. Serbia, while&#10;denouncing the assassinations, refused to apologize, stating they had&#10;nothing to do with the plot. Austria responded by declaring war on&#10;Serbia, which forced treaty-bound Russia to ally with Serbia. Germany,&#10;who was treaty-bound to Austria, declared war on Russia, causing France&#10;and Great Britain to come to Russia’s aid. World War I devastated&#10;Germany, which laid the fertile ground for the rise of nationalism and&#10;Hitler, which resulted in World War II.&#10;&#10;All of the death and destruction of these wars was a consequence of a&#10;chance meeting at a ball, plus countless other *butterfly effects*, such&#10;as Gavrilo stopping to buy a sandwich which happened to place him at the&#10;right time and place, and every other interaction that has ever taken&#10;place since the First Cause started the show. But such stories are&#10;deceptive because they take away from the inconceivably profound&#10;realization that every trivial act is also a result of everything that&#10;has happened since the beginning of time. Yes, it’s quite possible that&#10;WWI would have occurred in any case, but in this timeline of history,&#10;this is what *did* happen, just as you may not have spilled your drink&#10;if you hadn’t turned your head because you heard a weird sound, but you&#10;did because everything that has ever happened since the beginning of&#10;time was leading up to that moment. This may sound like there is no such&#10;thing as “free will,” but we won’t get into that now as it is addressed&#10;towards the end of the book.&#10;&#10;One of the classic “truly random” events in the Universe is radioactive&#10;decay, but only the decay of a single atom. As a group, the decay is&#10;entirely predictable, which is how we calculate half-lives of&#10;radioactive material. This is the same as saying we know that there is a&#10;1 in 366 chance of getting into a car accident on a 1,000-mile car trip,&#10;but it is impossible to predict the who, when, or where of any one&#10;particular accident. Insurance companies try to minimize the odds with&#10;reams of data on the probabilities of accidents regarding teen drivers,&#10;aggressive drivers, weather, speeding, impaired driving, driver error,&#10;distracted driving, etc., which narrows the range but still can’t&#10;predict one accident. Still, this does not make individual accidents&#10;random. Suppose Sally gets drunk because she just got fired for&#10;aggressive behavior, and she decides to drive home from the bar in a&#10;snowstorm while arguing with her husband on the cell phone and going 30&#10;miles an hour over the speed limit, and she gets into an accident with&#10;Bob. In that case, there is nothing random about that, nor is there&#10;anything random about how Bob’s car was where it was when it got hit.&#10;Both Sally and Bob were on a path resulting from a series of chaotic&#10;events (i.e., life). Each event increased or decreased the probability&#10;of an accident. In Sally’s case, those events clearly created a high&#10;probability scenario for an accident. Bob, on the other hand, being a&#10;careful driver who was paying attention and was going slow, had a very&#10;low probability of an accident, yet he got hit anyway. We would say this&#10;was a random event (“bad luck”) for Bob but a highly predictable event&#10;for Sally. In this scenario, “random” means an unpredictable yet&#10;deterministic chaotic system (Bob’s life) that influenced another&#10;unpredictable yet deterministic chaotic system (Sally’s life). Because&#10;neither system is predictable, it is impossible to predict when or if&#10;they will interact; thus, “random” is often synonymous with&#10;“theoretically unpredictable,” as this random accident was the effect of&#10;a cause created by the intersection of 2 chaotic systems.&#10;&#10;A more common example of this is the idea of a stock market. The price&#10;of a stock is unpredictable, but it is not truly random, as the price is&#10;determined by the individual actions of thousands of buyers and sellers,&#10;each making non-random decisions based on their financial interests.&#10;Each of these cause/effect chains is a system in and of itself, and all&#10;these systems combined form the larger system of a stock market.&#10;&#10;![](/home/jw/books/tholonia/chapters/Images/L-sys-2.png &quot;fig:&quot;)Chaos is&#10;*deterministic* because it adheres to rules and even has a pattern, but&#10;the effects over time create unpredictable results. Chaos does not&#10;happen in one moment. It happens over time, and what happens next&#10;depends on what happened before, making chaos a self-similar or&#10;self-referencing process. Because it is *change* that happens over time,&#10;there are two components to consider; a *growth factor* and a *limiting&#10;factor*. For example, in the image to the right, we start with a simple&#10;pattern that never changes but can replicate itself in its children, and&#10;after 10 generations, it turns into a tree. The *growth factor* is&#10;self-generating, and the *limiting factor* is that all of the variables&#10;(length, angle, color) are permanently fixed. Popular real-world chaotic&#10;systems are things like the weather, economics, growth patterns, etc..&#10;Still, in actuality, everything that grows, moves, or has energy moving&#10;through it, has elements of chaos in its system that are influenced by&#10;millions of variables forever changing.&#10;&#10;Below are some diagrams to help make this concept clearer.&#10;&#10;**Row A:** The top-left shows the changes to a simple form where a line&#10;half the length extends from its parent line at 20°. This newly extended&#10;line will then also have a line half its length extending from it, and&#10;so on. The top-right image is the same pattern, but with 90° instead of&#10;20°. They are side-by-side to show how the natural form of plants is the&#10;same pattern as a now-common man-made grid pattern. Why is that&#10;significant? Because this grid pattern was adopted as a way to grow and&#10;expand new territory more efficiently, which is why the architects of&#10;the New World adopted it in the 1700s. Thomas Jefferson first used this&#10;pattern to “gridify” the entire country to make it easier to expand&#10;into. City planners found the same pattern far more effective than the&#10;more organically formed cities of old Europe. The major driving force&#10;behind this pattern was financial, of course, and it’s no surprise that&#10;this efficient form of development appeared and grew in parallel with&#10;the industrial revolution and the radical expansion of city populations,&#10;such as London, which grew 600% from 1775 to 1885. We see this same&#10;evolution of patterns in biology, such as grid cells, which are the&#10;cells that allow us to navigate our environment and which form a&#10;triangular grid with their impulses. It may seem like a stretch to claim&#10;that the industrial revolution, capitalism, and suburban roads are just&#10;another instance of the same patterns that determine tissue growth and&#10;the stripes of a Zebra Fish, but that is precisely the case[2]. The only&#10;difference is the context in which these patterns are being applied and&#10;the resources at hand.&#10;&#10;**Row B:** The middle row shows the simplest of all forms, the triangle.&#10;In this case, a new line is always created at the end of the previous&#10;line but rotated left 120°. At the end of that child line, a new parent&#10;line is created but rotated in the opposite direction (whose child will&#10;also rotate right, and so on). In the left image, all variables remain&#10;the same. In the middle image, the deviation was allowed to wander 1° in&#10;either direction. In the right image, the deviation was allowed to&#10;wander in any direction. These images represent the three states of&#10;order; perfect and unchanging, transitioning, and total chaos.&#10;&#10;This is also an example of an instance of a relative duality. While the&#10;prime duality is that of primal nothingness and primal somethingness, a&#10;relative duality is that of a relative nothingness and a relative&#10;somethingness. In this case, the relative somethingness is the lines&#10;formed by the rule, and the relative nothingness is where there are no&#10;lines. Together they create a perfect form (according to the rules); in&#10;other words, an archetype. It is perfect because the rules are perfect.&#10;When we add a tiny bit of imperfection of 1° (or 0.27%) of randomness,&#10;the form is no longer perfect but still identifiable. With 100% of&#10;randomness, it is total chaos, a perfect mess. This is an example of the&#10;path from order to one type of chaos (the path from chaos to order is&#10;addressed in the chapter on energy).&#10;&#10;**Row C:** Because chaos is deterministic (but appears random), whatever&#10;a chaotic system does, it will do exactly the same way every time if all&#10;the variables remain the same. In our world, these variables are&#10;dynamic, so there will always be some changes to some variables. This is&#10;why all pine trees don’t look identical. The row shows five instances of&#10;the 5th generation of the same source pattern where slight variations in&#10;length and divergence were allowed. This is meant to demonstrate that&#10;while growth is a chaotic system, evolution is a chaotic system with&#10;some amount of randomness in it, for without those slight variations,&#10;nothing would ever change. Reality expands in chaos but evolves in&#10;randomness. At least, that is the premise we start from because random&#10;events can exist within the chaos of change, but the chaos of change can&#10;not exist in a random event, and the Universe is certainly a system of&#10;change.&#10;&#10;When looking at these images, remember that these are only 2-dimensional&#10;patterns of 10 or fewer generations from their starting point, with only&#10;length and divergence changing slightly. In the 3-dimensional world we&#10;live in, the starting point from which all form descends is the&#10;beginning of existence. The variables and generations at any and every&#10;moment since the beginning of time are countless, and the change in the&#10;variables range from minuscule to dramatic. The impossibility of&#10;accounting for all the details necessary to make a prediction of a&#10;chaotic system is why it is unpredictable.&#10;&#10;[1] Lorenz, Edward N. “**The Essence of Chaos**”. Seattle: Univ. of&#10;Washington Press, 2008. Appendix 1 “**The Butterfly Effect**”,&#10;&lt;http://climate.envsci.rutgers.edu/climdyn2017/LorenzButterfly.pdf&gt;.&#10;Lorenz was the founder of chaos theory which began with his 1963 paper&#10;“**Deterministic Nonperiodic Flow**”,&#10;&lt;https://journals.ametsoc.org/view/journals/atsc/20/2/1520-0469_1963_020_0130_dnf_2_0_co_2.xml&gt;&#10;&#10;[2] Heller, E., &amp; Fuchs, E. (2015). “**Tissue patterning and cellular&#10;mechanics**“. *The Journal of cell biology*, *211*(2), 219–231.&#10;&lt;https://doi.org/10.1083/jcb.201506106&gt;,&#10;&lt;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4621832/&gt;">
    </outline>
  </outline>
</outline>
  </body>
</opml>
